A Guide to the Fan Free Clinic Records, 1971-2006, undated
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Fan Free Clinic Records 1971-2006, undated
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
M 344
6 linear feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to VCU Libraries in August and December 2005 by Norma Schanz, executive director of the Fan Free Clinic in the early 1980s.
Historical Information
The Fan Free Clinic, Inc. was organized in Richmond, Virginia in 1970 by volunteer medical professionals, pastoral counselors and community volunteers. Three individuals, William Fitzhugh, an MCV resident, Mary File, an operating room nurse, and Robert Bluford, Jr., a director of the Presbyterian Church's work on college and university campuses over the south at the time, began planning in the summer of 1970 for what was to become the Fan Free Clinic. They opened the first Fan Free Clinic at 1103 Floyd Avenue in October 1970. Since then, the clinic has moved to several different locations. As of 2007, Fan Free Clinic is located at 1010 North Thompson Street. Initially, the free clinic was an emergency response to the medical and emotional issues that accompanied the influx of ill prepared young people into the inner city environment of Richmond's Fan District. Simultaneously, the free clinic found that its services were in demand by the broader inner city population. This varied clientele shared similar problems that had not yet been addressed adequately by the health care system.
As public health developed its responses to these rapidly growing community health issues, the free clinic was recognized and funded for its unique ability to reach persons at high risk who were reluctant to utilize public health facilities; reach and treat Richmond's homeless, indigent and/or sheltered population; provide volunteer services at low cost to public health's limited dollars; and provide services during night hours for persons who could not patronize clinics during traditional work hours.
In the 1970s, public health's emphasis in prevention was early diagnosis and treatment. Beginning in the 1980s, with the emerging AIDS epidemic, prevention education was prioritized. The free clinic was further recognized and funded for its experience in preventive communication with the targeted high risk populations and training and networking with service providers to bridge the gaps in service that result from indigency, fear and stigma. The free clinic's volunteer resources have stretched the available public monies to provide services at a level that otherwise could not have afforded.
As it remains today, the Fan Free Clinic's mission is to provide medical treatment, health education, and social services to those in the Richmond Metro area with limited access to care. The free clinic place special emphasis on welcoming the least served.
[Information taken from a Fan Free Clinic Manual with its written history, an excerpt taken from Robert Bluford, Jr.'s account of the formation of the Fan Free Clinic and the mission taken from the Fan Free Clinic website in March 2007, www.fanfreeclinic.org]
Scope and Content
The collection includes correspondence, memorabilia, videotapes, newspaper clippings, numerous photographs, various organizational minutes and reports, Fan Free Clinic newsletters, posters, and advertisements, and other published materials on Fan Free Clinic. The collection dates from the early 1970s to 2006. Within the collection there is an extensive amount of newspaper clippings focusing on the role of the clinic in Richmond, videotapes and photographs focusing on the Fan Free Clinic programs, special events such as the AIDSWALK: Richmond and the Tour de Friends in 2003, and HIV/AIDS awareness efforts and fundraisings.
Arrangement
The contents of this collection had been arranged chronologically and alphabetically in seven series, which are: Series I: Newspaper Clippings (1982-2007,undated); Series II: Organizational Files; 1971-2005; Series III: Publications (1971-2006,undated); Series IV: Memorabilia (circa 1980s-2000s, undated); Series V: Videotapes (1989, 1993, 2003, undated ); Series VI - Oversize (undated); and Series VII - Photographs and Slides (1980s-2000s, undated).
Contents List
- Newspaper Clippings 1982-2007, undated (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings 1982-1987 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Newspaper clippings 1988 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Newspaper clippings Sep. - Oct. 1989 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Newspaper clippings 1990 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Newspaper clippings Aug. 4, 1990 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Newspaper clippings 1992 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Newspaper clippings Feb. 1993 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Newspaper clippings Winter 1994 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Newspaper clippings 1995 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Newspaper clippings Jan. 1997 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Newspaper clippings Nov. 1997 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Newspaper clippings 1998 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Newspaper clippings 1999 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Newspaper clippings 1999 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Newspaper clippings 2000 (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Newspaper clippings 2001 (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Newspaper clippings 2002 (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Newspaper clippings 2003 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Newspaper clippings 2004 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Newspaper clippings 2005 (Box-folder 1:19)
  - Newspaper clippings undated (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Tour de Friends Media Coverage, September 2002 - July 2003 (Box-folder 1:21)
- Organizational Files 1971-2005 (Box 1-2)
  - Agenda for UWS Meeting 2004 (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Annual Reports 1998 - 1999 (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Board of Directors List 1971-2003 (Box-folder 1:24)
  - By Laws 1995 (Box-folder 1:25)
  - By Laws 1995 (Box-folder 1:25)
  - Capital Campaign 1997 (Box-folder 1:26)
  - City Council Member Lists undated (Box-folder 1:27)
  - Community Donations and In-Kind Contributions 1981 - 1999, undated (Box-folder 1:28)
  - Contact Information undated (Box-folder 1:29)
  - Correspondence 1972-2007 (Box-folder 1:30)
  - Fact Sheet undated (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Fan Free Clinic Manual with Introduction, Legal Facts, Medical Services, Information on STD's, AIDS/HIV, Birth Control, Contacts and Glossary undated (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Financial Statement 2003 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Fundraising Pospects and Documents 1994-2006 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - History undated (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Medical Terminology List undated (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Minutes/ Records of Board Meetings 1971-1981 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Orientation for New Volunteers Manual undated (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Personal Resource Development undated (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Richmond AIDS Ministry 2002-2003 (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Service Statistics 1995 (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Strategic Planning 1994-1997 (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Surveys/ Questionnaires undated (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Virginia HIV Community Planning Committee 1997 Comprehensive Plan 1997 (Box-folder 2:14)
  - Volunteers in Health Care 1999 (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Volunteers List and Program 1998 and undated (Box-folder 2:16)
- Publications 1986-2006, undated (Box 3-4)
  - AIDS/ STD News Report 1996-1997 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Brochures undated (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Cookbook Feb. 1990 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Fan Free Times 2005-2006 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Lambda Directory 2005-2006 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Let's Talk Newsletter 1989-2003 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Magazines with Articles on Fan Free Clinic 2000, 2001 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Posters and Advertisements (1 of 2) undated (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Posters and Advertisements (2 of 2) undated (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Publications of Other Organizations 1986-2001 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Publications of Other Organizations undated (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Virginia Department of Health Division of HIV/STD- Program Summary and Surveillance Quarterly 2000-2002 (Box-folder 4:5)
- Memorabilia undated (Box 5-6)
  - Award Certificate undated (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Balloon undated (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Bingo Card undated (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Condom undated (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Pleasure Cheques undated (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Stickers undated (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Miscellaneous Poem undated (Box-folder 5:7)
  - HIV/AIDS Collection Jar 2001 (Box 6 OVERSIZE)
  - AIDSWALK Richmond Button (2 round buttons) undated (Box 6 OVERSIZE)
  - AIDSWALK Richmond Button - "I'm Walking In Memory of:"(2 round buttons) undated (Box 6 OVERSIZE)
- Videotapes 1989, 1993, 2003, undated (Box 7-11)
  - AIDS Advocacy Training Part I, Nov. 5, 1993 (Box-folder 7:1)
  - AIDS Advocacy Training Part II, Nov. 5, 1993 (Box-folder 7:2)
  - AIDS Advocacy Training Part III, Nov. 5, 1993 (Box-folder 7:3)
  - AIDS Advocacy Training Part IV, Nov. 5, 1993 (Box-folder 7:4)
  - AIDS Advocacy Training (Part 1 of 2), Nov. 6, 1993 (Box-folder 8:1)
  - AIDS Advocacy Training (Part 2 of 2), Nov. 6, 1993 (Box-folder 8:2)
  - AIDS Conference (1 of 6), Oct. 14, 1989 (Box-folder 9:1)
  - AIDS Conference (2 of 6), Oct. 14, 1989 (Box-folder 9:2)
  - AIDS Conference (3 of 6), Oct. 14, 1989 (Box-folder 9:3)
  - AIDS Conference (4 of 6), Oct. 14, 1989 (Box-folder 9:4)
  - AIDS Conference (5 of 6), Oct. 14, 1989 (Box-folder 10:1)
  - AIDS Conference (6 of 6), Oct. 14, 1989 (Box-folder 10:2)
  - AIDS - The Compassionate Response (1 of 2), undated (Box-folder 10:3)
  - AIDS - The Compassionate Response (2 of 2), undated (Box-folder 10:4)
  - Rain: AIDS Skit, 1989 (Box-folder 11:1)
  - Tour de Friends 12 min. 2003 (Box-folder 11:2)
  - Tour de Friends Loop tape 2003 (Box-folder 11:3)
- Oversize Materials 1970-1971, 1989, 1998, 2005, undated (Box 12-13)
  - Posters 1989, 1998, 2005, undated (Box 12 OVERSIZE)
  - Fan Free Clinic Scrapbook, 1970-1971 (Box 13 OVERSIZE)
- Photographs and Slides 2003, undated (Box 14-16)
  - Photographs - AIDS Quilt Panel undated (Box-folder 14:1)
  - Photograph - Jim Beckner and others undated (Box-folder 14:2)
  - Photographs - Special Events - AIDSWALK: Richmond (1 of 2) undated (Box-folder 14:3)
  - Photographs - Special Events - AIDSWALK: Richmond (2 of 2) undated (Box-folder 14:4)
  - Photographs - Special Events - Drama/ Theatrical Performance, undated (Box-folder 14:5)
  - Photographs - Special Events - Sex Education, undated (Box-folder 14:6)
  - Photographs - Special Events - Tour de Friends, 2003 (Box-folder 14:7)
  - Photographs - Special Events - Miscellaneous (1 of 2), undated (Box-folder 14:8)
  - Photographs - Special Events - Miscellaneous (2 of 2), undated (Box-folder 14:9)
  - Photographs - Staff Gatherings, undated (Box-folder 14:10)
  - Photographs - Staff, Volunteers and New Clinic Building, undated (Box-folder 14:11)
  - Photographs - Staff, Volunteers and Old Clinic Building, undated (Box-folder 14:12)
  - Photographs - "UNTIL ITS OVER" Bell with AIDS ribbon engraving, undated (Box-folder 14:13)
  - Photographs - Miscellaneous, undated (Box-folder 14:14)
  - Photographs - Miscellaneous - Negatives, undated (Box-folder 14:15)
  - Slide Images - Art Show/Installations, undated (Box-folder 14:16)
  - Photographs - Page Magazine Ad on AIDS, undated (Box 15 OVERSIZE)
  - Album 1 - Fan Free Clinic Ten Year Anniversary, 1980 (Box 15 OVERSIZE)
  - Album 2 with photographs of FFC gatherings, AIDSWALK: Richmond, and other old and recent pictures of staff, volunteers, and clinic, undated (Box 16)
  - Album 2 Description Cards identifying people and events in the numbered photographs, undated (Box 16)
  - Album 3 with photographs of FFC gatherings, Ten year anniversary, AIDS Quilt Panels, AIDSWALK: Richmond, Staff pictures at Old Clinic facility, Photos of New Clinic Facility, and In Memoriam Photographs, undated (Box 16)
  - Album 3 Folder with loose photographs of FFC gatherings, and ten year anniversary, undated (Box 16)
  - Album 3 Description Cards identifying people and events in the numbered photographs, undated (Box 16)
  - Description Cards with no matching photographs, undated (Box 16)